Now, as we've been discussing, despite
some worrying economic results,
President Trump has been taking a victory lap
to mark the first 100 days of his second term,
going so far as to say his success surpasses
any in US history. We're here tonight in the
heartland of our nation to celebrate the
most successful first 100 days of any
administration in the history of our country.
And that's according to many, many people.
Well, perhaps not according to our next guest,
the presidential historian Timothy Naftali,
who puts the Trump presidency in full context
for Walter Isacson. Thank you, Christian John
and Tim Nfali. Welcome back to the show. Thank
you. Pleasure to be with you, Walter. So,
we're at the 100 day mark of this second Trump
administration. What's your take on it so far?
I think we should uh assess the the Trump 100
days uh in light of the golden gold standard
for 100 days. You know, that whole term comes
from the first term of Franklin Roosevelt and
Franklin Roosevelt's main theme was to banish fear
from the American space. Uh he wanted to restore
the American people's confidence in American
institutions, um banks, the federal government.
He wanted Americans to feel that they had some
capacity, predictive capacity over the future. Um,
and by those standards, I think u Donald Trump has
done the opposite. I think Donald Trump has tried
to introduce fear into the American space. fear
among American universities, fear among American
law firms, fear among international students
and recent immigrants, fear among members of
the Republican party on the Hill. So in that
sense, the 100 days that we have witnessed,
which have been as active and revolutionary as
FDR's 100 days, um have had the exact opposite
objective. And I think that's why um it'll be safe
to say that liberal and conservative historians
in the future will look upon these 100 days as
destructive. Well, one of the big differences
between the 100 days of Franklin Roosevelt and
of Trump is that Franklin Roosevelt did most
of his work by passing laws through Congress. I
think there were 12 major pieces of legislation.
Trump has not followed that route. Why? And what
does that mean? Franklin Roosevelt um even though
it was it was a 100 days period led by Congress,
many people associated this activity with Franklin
Roosevelt. And right Franklin Roosevelt um in his
third fireside chat after the 100 days made clear
to everyone that what he was doing was in the
American tradition that he was simply implementing
laws passed by Congress. So he too understood that
the American tradition was not to have a dictator.
Fast forward to our current time, President Trump
has sought to act as if he were the only branch of
government. Uh we do not live in a dictatorship,
but he has acted in the style of a dictator. Wait,
let me stop you there, which is whose fault is
that? I mean, it's is Congress is the thing not
standing up to him? Well, he hasn't encouraged
uh two things. He has gone about his business
acting both rhetorically and uh and physically as
if there is no other uh branch of government. And
indeed when branches of government have stood up
to him, he has been vicious in denouncing them.
We we we just saw a perw walk of a American
judge a judge. So, so when the other branches
of government have sought to oppose him, he has
not acted in the spirit of Franklin Roosevelt by
speaking of the national government, he has talked
about the presidency as the seat of all power. So
yes, whose fault is it that there is a permissive
environment for this activity? Of course, it's the
fault of elected Republicans um who have been,
as we learned from Senator Macowski, Marcowski,
fearful of opposing their president. So by that's
that's why I'm talking about the installation of
fear not simply in private institutions but in
the Republican party itself. Well, let let's go
to that Senator Bowski quote because it struck
me. Uh she said, "We are all afraid. We're in
a time and a place I've not been here before.
I'm oftenimes very anxious myself about using
my voice. Retaliation is real." What do you make
of that? It chills me. It's it's a it's a chilling
statement um by the senator and it it it echoes
something that um Mitt Romney I think wrote in his
diary. It appears in his authorized biography
where where he had hired when he was senator,
he had hired security for his family and he wrote,
I think it was during the first impeachment in
2019 that he understood why there were so many
of his colleagues who knew that they should be
voting for impeachment but were afraid to because
they were afraid of the effect on their families,
physical effect. and he said, you know, they can't
afford 24/7 security the way I can. So that echoed
the fear that existed back in the first Trump
administration. We saw that also with the way
in which the Senate dealt with the confirmations
of President Trump's uh new cabinet. Uh there were
a number of senators who found a way to leak the
fact they were not happy with some of President
Trump's choices. for example, um, uh, Secretary
now Secretary Hexiff at the Pentagon, uh,
or John or RFK Jr. at Health and Human Services.
But in the end, they were so fearful of a primary
challenge and I think also fearful of their own
supporters that they fell into line. Well, wait,
there's a big difference between being fearful of
a primary challenge because you voted against the
way people in your district may want or being
fearful of physical harm and you got to hire a
bodyguard. What do you think this is? Well,
Walter, let's make clear that the the first
uh branding of this new Trump administration,
in my view, was the pardoning of the January 6th
felons. When you pardon uh violent felons, you are
sending a signal about law and order in America.
And and unlike um President Andrew Johnson, not
one of my favorites, but President Johnson when
he issued a blanket pardon to the leaders of the
rebellion in 1868, he did not um deny that they
had committed a crime. His pardon talks about
those who led a rebellion against the lawfully
authorized government of the United States.
Um but when Donald Trump issued his pardon,
he issued it after he said uh after four years of
injustice making the point that the January 6th
insurrection was just. So when you set that kind
of tone, you are inviting vigilanteism. I'm not
saying that Donald Trump wants it. I want everyone
to understand I'm talking about a spirit here. But
but there are many Americans who might be troubled
who might see the way in which the president is
speaking of January 6 as license to engage in
violence against those who opposed Donald Trump.
One of the uh historical comparisons that come
to mind is with Andrew Jackson who very much was
a populist expanding executive power and in one of
his actions which was removal of Native Americans,
the Indian removal, it's almost in some ways uh
echoes the uh removal of unauthorized immigrants
that Trump is trying to do. And when the Supreme
Court said don't do that to Jackson, just like
they've just said it, don't do that to Trump.
The tale is that Jackson basically intimated
Chief Justice Marshall has made his decision. Now
let us see him enforce it. Do you worry that Trump
may just defy like that Supreme Court? I don't
know what Donald Trump will do when push comes
to shove because I anticipate Donald Trump will
lose a series of very important cases. I suspect,
I'm not a lawyer and I don't play one on
television, but I do know something about federal
um assistance to universities. I think Donald
Trump's uh DOJ will lose the case against Harvard.
I I suspect he's going to lose the case regarding
birthright citizenship. I assume he's going to
lose some of the immigration cases. He's already
started to lose them. And and I think there will
be enormous pressure uh from the MAGA wing on
this president to defy the courts. And I cannot
predict what Donald Trump will do. I I hope that
he will conclude that he can't defy the courts,
but I can't predict that because this Donald
Trump is an unleashed, unplugged Donald Trump
from the person we saw in the first term. The
first term, Donald Trump um accepted uh having
people around him who could dissuade him from his
impulses. In the second term, Donald Trump made
clear in the campaign, by the way, that he wanted
no guardrails. He wanted no so-called adults. He
wanted unfiltered Trumpism in his second term.
Whether or not unfiltered Trumpism means defying
the court and talking like Jackson is something
to be seen. What happens if he does defy a court
order? Who could step in? We know the FBI is
pretty much under his control. Even to some
extent it seems the top officers of the military
the uh US attorney maybe in Washington is a
loyalist who could step in under my understanding
of constitutional tradition. Um there isn't anyone
who can step in because we have three equal
branches. Um the Supreme Court has a marshall
service to protect the lives of the Supreme
members of the Supreme Court. Thank goodness
in this very pitched dangerous moment um it's very
important for for us to have a Supreme Court that
doesn't have to worry about its physical security.
But the Supreme Court doesn't have um doesn't
doesn't have an army. One solutary um one one sign
of hope um is that in our country uh when you take
an oath the oath of office um you take it to the
constitution and even though Donald Trump doesn't
accept the norm that might not accept the norm um
that the president um must defer to the Supreme
Court on on matters of the constitution. It is not
clear that the leadership of the US military would
accept the commander-in-chief's interpretation
of this norm. I am not suggesting nor do I wish
that the US military should have to intervene
to preserve our constitution because that puts
us in a that puts us in a category of nations that
where we do not wish to be. But keep in mind that
the leaders of our military do not give an oath to
the president. It's to the constitution. But wait,
do you worry then about the way he changed
the chairman of the joint chiefs of staff,
the way he put a somewhat unconventional pick as
secretary of defense, all loyalist to him? Yes, I
worry. I worry deeply, Walter. One of the lessons
of of of studying the periods in our history when
we've had quasi authoritarians in power is that
the system can correct itself or write itself.
And usually it writes itself because members
of of the I don't want to use the term elite
but among among those with power and influence in
our society come to an a bipartisan understanding
that that that authoritarian action threatens
the fabric of of who we are of our society.
And so in 1974 you had elected Republicans come
to the conclusion that Richard Nixon had to go.
In the 1950s, you had elected Republicans who
came to the conclusion that Joe McCarthy's
um reign of terror had to end. That's how our
system works. It it it doesn't work because
the opponents to the president succeed. Are you
seeing some signs that that could happen? Are
there things changing? Uh not yet. I saw glimmers
of this when a few Republican senators decided to
send a a note of dis disapproval to the president
regarding tariffs on Canada. But but those
senators understood that they lack the power to
change the president's approach on tariffs towards
Canada. But they did send a signal. Um what I am
seeing though are the beginnings of a retrenchment
on the part of the president that indicate to me
that the president's president and his inner team
think they might be losing popular support. So we
are seeing the president pull back a little bit
on the issue of international students. We are we
it's not quite clear what's going to happen to the
liberation day tariffs which have been universally
denounced for being stupid besides being high.
They they don't actually have any e economic
logic attached to them and the public isn't
buying them. The president's approval ratings on
the economy are lower than they have been that I
believe they're lower than they were in the first
term on the economy. So the president himself is
retrenching a little. Um so I see a little bit
of institutional push back on the hill. I see
a lot more institutional push back on the part
of universities and some law firms. Um so we're
beginning to see a reawakening of of the American
constitutional order. But let's be fair and let's
be clear about this. For the first twothirds
of this 100 days, it it appeared that the
American constitutional system was asleep. and the
president was acting without any push backs. The
situation has changed and I think will continue to
change. One of the things that uh has driven his
popularity is he's tapped into resentments,
resentments against the elite that you just
mentioned might be there to save us. Uh I think at
one point in the campaign rally in 2024, he said,
"I am your warrior. I am your justice for those
who have been wronged and betrayed. I am your
retribution. Yes. He's even pushed retribution
against people like Cheney or against the law
firms and others. Do you think this spirit of
retribution is something that he's actually tapped
into? And how dangerous is that? Well, there's no
doubt in my mind that he has tapped into a popular
desire uh for for change and in some cases for
retribution. I think uh the disqu in our country
um goes back to the great recession and the
unequal recovery that American re that regions
of this country uh experienced. I I don't doubt
that the pandemic sharpened um unhappiness and
divisions in our country. I think I think about
you know 15 20 years from now we're going to have
pandemic studies in various universities because
I don't think we fully absorbed or processed the
actual effect political cultural and social of the
pandemic on our country let alone the world. So
yes there was a lot of disquite and anger that he
could tap into. If you look at Nixon's campaign,
he ran on resentments to the elite. So did Andrew
Jackson. We've had this before. He's he ran on
on resentments. But what he didn't promise
was retribution. That's the key difference.
He wanted retribution and and he tried to use his
government to achieve it, but but good government
Republicans pushed back and wouldn't allow him to
do what he wanted to do with the IRS. you know,
the enemy's list was initially his idea as a tax
list and he was never able to implement it. Um,
my point simply is that American leaders have
tapped into resentment, whether it was resentment
uh in the south for the civil rights revolution.
Yes. What Donald Trump did that's so different is
that he made retribution his governing philosophy
and he told everyone he would and now he's doing
it. Now, the question I have for fellow Americans
is, is that who we are? Is that how we want to
be governed? And I'm not convinced, Walter,
that there is a sustainable, broad governing
coalition behind a government of retribution, but
maybe I'm an optimist. I don't know. Tim Nali,
thank you so much for joining us again. Thank
you for asking me on. Thank you, Walter.
[Music]